{"tossups": [{"question": "The Committee of Five, or Petka, led this country, and before World War Two, Carpathian Ruthenia was part of this nation, which allied with Yugoslavia and Romania in the Little Entente. Thomas Masaryk helped create this country whose soldiers fought in a Legion along the Trans-Siberian Railway. Edvard Bene\u0161 [[BEH-nesh]] led this country when the Sudetenland [[soo-DEH-ten-lahnd]] was annexed after the Munich Agreement. For ten points, name this former Central European country whose western portion was turned into a protectorate by Nazi Germany during World War Two.", "answer": "<b><u>Czechoslovakia</u></b> (or <b><u>\u010ceskoslovensko</u></b>; do not accept or prompt on \"Czech Republic,\" \"Slovak Republic,\" or \"Slovakia\")", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "In this state, a Loyalist mistook Henry Lee for Banastre [[BAH-nah-ster]] Tarleton in an engagement known as Pyle\u2019s Hacking Match. A horse was shot from under General Charles Cornwallis during a battle in this state which inspired the quote, \u201cAnother such victory will ruin the British army.\u201d That pyrrhic victory for the British was fought in this state at Guilford Court House, near modern-day Greensboro. For ten points, name this state whose capital was named for Sir Walter Raleigh.", "answer": "<b><u>North Carolina</u></b>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "One work by this composer, focusing on the dedication of a theatre in Pest [[PESHT]], laments the Ottoman conquest of Athens. Another work by this composer commemorates the result of the Battle of Vitoria, a defeat for Joseph Bonaparte. This composer of <em>Wellington\u2019s Victory</em> changed the original dedication of a work containing a C-minor funeral march from one specific ruler to a generic \u201cgreat man.\u201d Napoleon was the original dedicatee of the \u201cEroica\u201d Symphony by, for ten points, what composer of <em>F\u00fcr Elise</em>?", "answer": "Ludwig van <b><u>Beethoven</u></b>", "metadata": "Fine Arts - Auditory Fine Arts"}, {"question": "A hymn written in favor of the \"Gathering\" of these groups was written by George Loveless, one of the Tolpuddle Martyrs. The Webb siblings wrote a history of these groups, including their \"New Model\" form. Many of these groups signed the Warwick Agreement, allying with the Labour party. In 1871, these groups were legalized under Lord Derby's ministry, but these groups were previously banned under the Combination Acts. Organizing the 1926 General Strike, for ten points, what are these groups which represent laborers?", "answer": "Trade <b><u>Union</u></b>s in the United Kingdom (or Labor <b><u>Union</u></b>s)", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "This company\u2019s main product may have been inspired by the French beverage Vin Mariani [[mah-ree-AH-nee]]. During Asa Candler's time leading this company, it began bottling operations in Chattanooga. Despite positive taste tests, this company's 1985 \"New\" version of its flagship product was highly criticized. This company, which was founded by John Pemberton, launched its most popular drink during Prohibition in Georgia. For ten points, name this soft drink company, known for its rivalry with Pepsi.", "answer": "The <b><u>Coca-Cola</u></b> Company (accept <b><u>Coke</u></b>)", "metadata": "Trash - Trash"}, {"question": "In 2019, this series was remade for French television under the title <em>Mouche</em> [[MOOSH]]. This television show was adapted from a 2013 one-woman play at the Edinburgh Fringe Festival. <em>Enola Holmes</em> director Harry Bradbeer directed every episode of this series other than the pilot, in which the protagonist steals a sculpture of a woman\u2019s torso from her stepmother after being denied a loan for her failing caf\u00e9. The winner of the 2019 Primetime Emmy for Outstanding Comedy Series, for ten points, what is this television show starring Phoebe Waller-Bridge?", "answer": "<em><b><u>Fleabag</u></b></em>", "metadata": "Trash - Trash"}, {"question": "When the Sociedad de Beneficencia [[soh-cee-eh-DAHD deh beh-neh-fee-SEN-see-ah]] did not offer this person its presidency, she started a charitable foundation in her own name. A city built by that foundation was temporarily renamed Ciudad General Belgrano following the \"Liberating Revolution\" that removed this woman\u2019s husband from power. The title \u201cSpiritual Leader of the Nation\u201d was given to, for ten points, what suffragette and supporter of the <em>descamisados</em>, whose life story was depicted in a namesake Andrew Lloyd Webber musical?", "answer": "<b><u>E</u></b>va <b><u>Per\u00f3n</u></b> (accept <b><u>E</u></b>vita <b><u>Per\u00f3n</u></b>; prompt on \"Evita\")", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {"question": "This man, born in Lower Silesia, began his military career as a cavalry reconnaissance officer. The identity of this man's killer has been debated for decades, with suspects including Cedric Popkin's anti-aircraft gun and flying ace Arthur Roy Brown. This soldier commanded Jasta 11 [[YAH-stuh ELF]] as part of the larger \"Flying Circus\" unit. For ten points, name this colorfully-nicknamed ace German fighter pilot credited with 80 air combat victories in World War One.", "answer": "The <b><u>Red Baron</u></b> (or Manfred Albrecht Freiherr von <b><u>Richthofen</u></b>; or Baron von <b><u>Richthofen</u></b>)", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "In 2000, John Poulos and James Hoover founded this company in Canada. Sidney Powell claimed to have evidence from a Venezuelan military official proving this company\u2019s products were defective. Mike Lindell of My Pillow was the subject of a defamation lawsuit from this company, whose central products have cumulative and ranked-choice options. Potential tampering with this company's products in Wisconsin and Georgia partly led to a hand recount during the 2020 presidential election. For ten points, name this company which makes electronic voting equipment.", "answer": "<b><u>Dominion</u></b> Voting Systems Corporation", "metadata": "Current Events - Current Events"}, {"question": "This president defended Elizabeth Jennings Graham in a court case that helped pave the way for the desegregation of streetcars in his home state. The <em>New York World</em> wrote that during this man's time in office, \u201cno duty was neglected in his administration, and no adventurous project alarmed the nation.\" This president signed into effect the Pendleton Civil Service Reform Act after Charles Guiteau assassinated his predecessor. For ten points, name this 21st president and successor to James Garfield.", "answer": "Chester Alan <b><u>Arthur</u></b>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "This man stayed in his seat while rioters threw rocks and bottles at him in the Saint-Jean-Baptiste Day parade. The \u201cmania\u201d for this man abated after he married Margaret Sinclair, and to patriate the Constitution, this man's minister, John Turner, created the Victoria Charter. This man enforced the War Measures Act after James Cross and Pierre Laporte were kidnapped by the FLQ. This leader defused the October Crisis and made his nation officially bilingual. For ten points, name this Canadian prime minister, the father of Justin.", "answer": "<b><u>P</u></b>ierre <b><u>Trudeau</u></b> (prompt on <b><u>Trudeau</u></b>)", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "This \"Prairie Province\" is the only one without natural borders.", "answer": "<b><u>Saskatchewan</u></b>", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {"question": "This state's Uinta Mountains contain the Dinosaur National Monument, site of a 1950s activism campaign against the proposed Echo Park Dam. This state is the site of Promontory Summit, where two lines from Sacramento to Omaha were joined to create the first Transcontinental Railroad. The Mountain Meadows Massacre occurred in this state, which was settled by pioneers led by Brigham Young. For ten points, name this state whose population is over fifty percent Mormon.", "answer": "<b><u>Utah</u></b>", "metadata": "Geography - Geography"}, {}, {"question": "After the Civil War, this general claimed \u201call, all was lost, except my debts.\u201d Spencer repeating rifles helped one general overrun this man\u2019s defensive fortifications during the Tullahoma Campaign, which followed this man\u2019s defeat at Stones River. This man was replaced by Joseph Johnston after a defeat that included fighting at Missionary Ridge. That defeat occurred after this man avenged himself on William Rosecrans at a battle along a namesake tributary of the Tennessee River. For ten points, name this Confederate general who won the Battle of Chickamauga.", "answer": "Braxton <b><u>Bragg</u></b>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {}, {"question": "Journalist Walter Duranty misled Western audiences about this event by describing it as \"an exaggeration or malignant propaganda.\" Robert Conquest discussed this event in <em>The Harvest of Sorrow</em>. While living in Stavropol, Mikhail Gorbachev barely survived this event, in which his father and sisters were killed. This man-made disaster likely occurred in part to weaken the <em>Kulak</em> class who resisted the process of collectivization by Stalin's government. For ten points, name this 1932 to 1933 famine in Soviet Ukraine.", "answer": "<b><u>Holodomor</u></b> (accept The <b><u>Great Famine</u></b>; accept <b><u>Famine</u></b> in the <b><u>Ukraine</u></b> before mentioned)", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {}, {"question": "The Take Care clause is found in this article of the U.S. Constitution, which requires a two-thirds majority in the Senate prior to a treaty going into effect. The phase \u201chigh crimes and misdemeanors\u201d appears in this article, whose Section One, Clause Seven requires that a certain salary remain at $400,000 for an entire term. The Electoral College was established in this article, whose fourth section deals with impeachment. For ten points, name this article of the U.S. Constitution which outlines the powers of the Executive Branch.", "answer": "Article <b><u>Two</u></b> (accept <b><u>Second</u></b> Article)", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {}, {"question": "Followers of this man were opposed by a rival group known as the Palleschi [[pah-LEH-shee]]. The \u201cWeepers\u201d supported this man who befriended the author of <em>Oration on the</em> <em>Dignity of Man</em>, Pico Della Mirandola. This \u201cman was ruined with his new order of things\u201d according to Machiavelli, who referred to this man as being inadequately armed to enforce his beliefs. Charles VIII\u2019s invasion was welcomed by this man, who ordered the burning of sinful objects in the Bonfire of the Vanities. For ten points, name this Dominican friar who preached extensively in Florence.", "answer": "Girolamo <b><u>Savonarola</u></b>", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {}, {"question": "The <em>maenianum secundum</em> was a section of this structure in which ordinary citizens could watch events. For the opening of this structure, one emperor gave two events called <em>naumachia</em> [[now-MAY-kee-ah]], which lasted until its <em>hypogeum</em> [[hai-puh-JEE-um]] was built to support other activities. This landmark's construction was started by Emperor Vespasian and completed by his son, Titus. Also known as the Flavian Amphitheatre, for ten points, what is this structure in central Rome which hosted gladiator fights?", "answer": "<b><u>Colosseum</u></b> (accept <b><u>Flavian Amphitheatre</u></b> before mentioned)", "metadata": "History - Ancient History"}, {}, {"question": "This man was the namesake of a pottery club founded by Edith Guerrier and Edith Brown of the Saturday Evening Girls Club to help provide young women with income. This man commanded an artillery detachment during an expedition to capture a region of Maine after it had been taken over by the British. That disastrous 1779 Penobscot Expedition occurred several years after this man undertook a midnight ride to warn minutemen of the approaching British. For ten points, name this Bostonian silversmith.", "answer": "Paul <b><u>Revere</u> </b>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {}, {"question": "<b><u>This event was prompted by attempts at tax collection by John Bampton. John</u></b> <b><u>of Gaunt's Savoy Palace was destroyed during this event, which was ended after</u></b> <b><u>Henry Despenser won the Battle of (+)</u> North Walsham. Future king Henry IV was almost executed after being captured during this event. A meeting at Smithfield during this event resulted in William (*) </b>Walworth knifing one man to death. For ten points, what rebellion, led by Jack Straw and Wat Tyler, nearly ended the reign of Richard II of England?", "answer": "<b><u>Peasant</u></b>s\u2019 Revolt (accept <b><u>Wat Tyler</u></b>\u2019s Revolt before mentioned; accept <b><u>Great</u></b> <b><u>Rising</u></b>; accept \"Rebellion\" or \"Uprising\" in place of \"Revolt\")", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "<b><u>In what is now this state, the Second Battle of Vinegar Hill was fought during</u></b> <b><u>the Castle Hill Rebellion. Mid-nineteenth century modernization efforts in this state</u></b> <b><u>were overseen by Lachlan (+)</u> Macquarie [[LAH-kluhn muh-KWAH-ree]]. Land in this state belonging to the \u201cO\u2019Brien Estate\u201d was turned into (*) </b>Bondi Beach. A series of gold rushes in the mid-nineteenth century set the stage for a rivalry between this state\u2019s major city and Melbourne. For ten points, what Australian state's capital was named for Thomas Townshend, First Viscount Sydney?", "answer": "<b><u>New South Wales</u></b>", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {"question": "<b><u>At a 1920 convention held in this state, Carrie Chapman Catt founded the</u></b> <b><u>League of Women Voters. One 1906 novel set in this state attempted to expose the</u></b> <b><u>harsh living conditions for its largest city's (+)</u> immigrant population. In this state in 2017, a bill prohibiting police from arresting someone based on immigration status was signed by Governor (*) </b>Bruce Rauner. For ten points, name this state, the setting of the novel which prompted the Meat Inspection Act, <em>The Jungle</em>.", "answer": "<b><u>Illinois</u></b>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "<b><u>One work from this artist depicts a large ponderosa pine tree on D. H.</u></b> <b><u>Lawrence's ranch, and this artist produced a series of cloudscapes while living at</u></b> <b><u>Abiqui\u00fa [[AB-ih-kyoo]]. This person caused a sensation as the subject of a 1921</u></b> <b><u>exhibition of mostly (*)</u> nude photographs by photographer Alfred Stieglitz, whom she later married. </b><em><b>Jimson Weed</b></em><b> and (*) </b><em>Cow's Skull: Red, White, and Blue</em> are among the best known works of, for ten points, what \"Mother of American modernism,\" known for her paintings of New Mexico landscapes, animal bones, and flowers?", "answer": "Georgia <b><u>O'Keeffe</u></b>", "metadata": "Fine Arts - Visual Fine Arts"}, {"question": "<b><u>William Brownrigg was sent a sample of this resource by Charles Wood that</u></b> <b><u>was the subject of numerous experiments. Charles III gave the entire government</u></b> <b><u>supply of this resource to Pierre-Fran\u00e7ois Chabaneau [[shah-bah-NOH]] for research,</u></b> <b><u>resulting in the creation of its malleable form. (+)</u> Antonio de Ulloa [[oo-YOH-ah]] is said to have been the first European to discover this metal, which was often discarded due to the belief that it made (*) </b>gold impure. Derived from a term meaning \u201clittle silver,\u201d for ten points, what precious metal has atomic number 78 and chemical symbol Pt [[PEE-TEE]]?", "answer": "<b><u>Platinum</u></b> (accept <b><u>Pt</u></b> before mentioned; prompt on \u201cplatino\u201d)", "metadata": "Science - Chemistry"}, {"question": "<b><u>Two answers required. These two countries engaged in the diplomatic Madrid</u></b> <b><u>Principles and Prague Process. These two countries fought a war that included</u></b> <b><u>Operation Ring and the Khojaly [[HO-jah-luh]] Massacre. Operation (+)</u> Goranboy was launched by one of these two countries in a conflict that ended with the Bishkek Protocol. These two nations fought for the Lachin [[LAH-cheen]] Corridor in a 1988 to 1994 war in (*) </b>Nagorno-Karabakh [[kah-ruh-BAHK]]. For ten points, name these two nations in the Caucasus, governed from Yerevan and Baku.", "answer": "Republic of <b><u>Armenia</u></b> and Republic of <b><u>Azerbaijan</u></b> (accept <b><u>Hayastani</u> </b>Hanrapetut'yun for <b><u>Armenia</u></b>; accept <b><u>Azerbaycan</u></b> Respublikasi for <b><u>Azerbaijan</u></b>)", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {"question": "<b><u>This period was preceded by one nicknamed \"closing curtain,\" during which</u></b> <b><u>the slogan \"Sonn\u014d j\u014di\" [[SOH-NOH JO-EE]] was used. This era, which followed the</u></b> <b><u>Bakumatsu period, accelerated (+)</u> industrialization in its country under the national slogan \"Enrich the country, strengthen the military.\" Dissatisfaction with reforms during this period led to the Satsuma Rebellion, in which disaffected (*) </b>samurai revolted. This period included the passage of the proto-constitutional Charter Oath. For ten points, name this era of modernization which began after the fall of the Tokugawa Shogunate.", "answer": "<b><u>Meiji</u></b> Restoration (accept <b><u>Meiji</u></b> Period; accept <b><u>Meiji</u></b> Renewal)", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {"question": "<b><u>A crossing at this battle was planned at Skinkers Neck, and artillery was</u></b> <b><u>placed at Stafford Heights. Confusion at this battle arose from using the less forceful</u></b> <b><u>phrase \"to seize\" rather than \"to (+)</u> carry.\" The Right Grand Division at this battle was led by Edwin Vose Sumner. A plan to cross the Rappahannock River to reach Richmond at this battle failed and forced a confrontation at (*) </b>Marye's Heights after pontoon bridges were assembled. For ten points, name this 1862 battle in Virginia, a victory for Robert E. Lee.", "answer": "Battle of <b><u>Fredericksburg</u></b>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "<b><u>This city's \"Ladies\" donated diamonds so that George Washington's men</u></b> <b><u>would have enough shoes and socks at Yorktown. This city's first mass was</u></b> <b><u>commemorated by El Templete [[tem-PLEH-teh]], whose pillars are crowned by</u></b> <b><u>pineapples. In 1762, British troops under George (+)</u> Keppel captured this city and its Morro Castle. Under Meyer Lansky and Lucky Luciano, the Mafia introduced casinos and gambling to this city for the (*) </b>Batista regime. The Castro government nationalized businesses in, for ten points, what capital of Cuba?", "answer": "<b><u>Havana</u></b> (accept La <b><u>Habana</u></b>)", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {}], "bonuses": []}